recording before we get thunderstormed
on oh my gosh I wish you could see it
it's
coming how do you get a good job inter
interview how do you execute on a job
interview what should you say in a job
interview and there have been lots of
opinions about this there's an email
there's a chat that came through I'm not
putting chat on the screen anymore by
the way in case you had noticed so the
question was let me see if I can find it
um somebody
said I would job interview with a client
tomorrow do you have any advice for me
so I have lots of advice and I would ask
you like us combine it with other
people's advice first of all I want to
read some advice from damad Dutch it
says regarding a job interview one of
the best pieces of advice I've ever seen
was that when you ask when they ask you
if have any questions you you start to
use the word when they hire you so
things like when they hire you so when
so when I start working with you uh what
are the projects that I could start
using you know what are the technologies
that I would be immediately using so
you're talking about what's going on
already at that moment right you're you
get them thinking in their brain that
they're already most people that are
hiring you they already know this trick
they've heard about this trick and it's
just a matter of you using executing on
the trick but the whole point is getting
them to think in their mind that they
that they've actually hired you um a bit
of I'm just going to throw out the other
advice that comes to mind um obviously
we already talked about the rum there's
a whole video about the rum the thing
with the rais that you got to keep in
mind is that the rais are I mean why are
you taking advice about a job interview
from a guy living in his car currently
by the way I'm just going on a trip in
my car I'm not living in
it so um because because I have the
money to pay for a trip in my car how
about that okay uh so watch the video
about the rais right the rais is the
discussion Point that's the thing you
can refer to your rum because they
likely haven't read your rum most of the
people don't care about your resum
that's what the video is about and so
what you can do is you can say well as I
mentioned in my risim I did blah blah
blah so when they ask you a thing refer
to the risim right so keep referring
back to the rum when you can um because
that will give them something to Circle
they'll Circle that item on the rume and
then when they they go back after the
fact when they're eval evaluating as a
candidate you'll have caused a situation
where they actually took took notes on
your rum and that will make you stand
out against everybody else nobody else
is going to do that right there most the
other people are just going to talk
they're not going to refer to the Raz
and the person may or may not take notes
because they're probably interviewing 10
20 30 candidates it depends on how many
they're doing but if you refer to the
rais and you encourage the person to
take notes on the rais indirectly you
might end up getting more visibility
later on when I go through the rais
stack and they're evaluating it when
they're going through the raisme stack
they'll come to your raisme and they'll
see that they took more notes on your
raisme than somebody else and they said
oh hey here's a good thing here and you
can't refer back to the rum unless you
have a good rum which means you've got
specific metrics and stuff separate
video on that so that would be the
biggest thing the this the number one
thing which damama dut Al required also
recommended is getting them mentally
thinking they've already hired you right
so so the questions would be um things
like how what what would be you know
when I start working for you what is
this what is the one technology and by
the way more precisely the better what
is the one thing that I can Master
immediately so that when I work for you
I can immediately be productive that is
probably the most valuable question you
could ever ask and and if probably
people are going to expect that you have
heard that from me or somebody else
right the reason that that particular
way of phrasing it is so important is
because you are already mentally putting
yourself in the place that assuming you
have the job that nails for them the
fact that you have the motivation to do
it they are going to know that you want
the job because you're already mentally
painting a picture for them that you've
already got the job so they're already
assuming and mind that you have the job
and you're already starting to you're
demonstrating that you have already
assumed that you're going to get that
job so saying things like when if I get
this job if I decide to take this job if
this turns out to be the job for me that
kind of stuff is not going to get you
the job even if you're not sure about
the job you need to talk in the
interview like you have this job like
this is the only job that matters like
this is the one job that you want above
every other job and you want to you want
to convey that kind kind of feeling when
you're doing the job interview because
that makes them make they have a whether
or not you end up taking that job or
another job the perception is that
they're going to want they're going to
think that this is this is the one that
you really want and that this is this is
then you can go ahead and you can
totally commit to that so again saying
things like when I start this when I
start this job so when I start this job
on this great team uh what is the number
one thing that I would need to know to
be immediately productive and the thing
that's cool about that is that causes
them to also think of specifically about
what your assignment would be so they
have to like dig apart well what we have
this over here we have this over here we
have this over there so that causes them
to immediately kind of find you that
first project that first task that you
have to do they might say something like
well we would immediately pair you with
so and so because you need to get really
good with kubernetes or you get need to
get really good with red hat satellite
or or anible right so they would
immediately tell you those things that
you have to do and then you can like you
can sell it on that point again that is
it's a single most most important thing
you can do um the SEC there are a couple
secondary things and then some
absolutely don't do things and I'll
mention those two the second thing that
I would say when you're doing the job
interview is when it comes time to ask
questions sh demonstrate interest in the
company specifically this this will go
so far for separating you from everybody
else there everybody else who's in there
joining the job
interview almost all of them will not
have researched the company and you will
already have done this if you followed
my other advice earlier on when you're
preparing to get a job or preparing to
learn because you have already decided
what you want to do every day you have
already targeted about five companies
that represent the kind of work that you
want to do possibly the company you're
interviewing for which means you've
already looked at those companies you've
already researched them to see what the
jobs are how they're operated and you've
got a mentor Andor a recruiter and so
you're already dealing every day with
the responsibilities and tasks of that
job so you will have already done
research if if you've done this right
you will already have done research
about the company that you're in for
this isn't some random interview this is
this is you've already done the research
and before you go in for the interview
you should have spent an extra amount of
time reviewing the missions uh the
mission of the company that you're
interviewing for so that means you need
to demonstrate legitimate authentic
interest in the mission of the company
whether or not you actually want you
care that much about the mission which
you probably should don't lie but you
should demonstrate authentic interest so
when they give you a chance to up ask a
question the first question I would say
it would be the softball question
because I would want to end with the
other question that we already talked
about so I kind of did it in reverse
order right so the first question I
would say is what do you ask them some
specific question that's related to the
company like if you were interviewing
with such and such you'd say what is
your position on AI in the industry and
how has it impacted you I understand
you've added it to your it Department
what where do you see its position in
the company I noticed that you use it
for X and Y specific thing which was in
the news recently right so now you're
demon demonstrating legitimate sincere
interest in the company and the
company's Mission and the company's
controversies the thing that are making
the company uh you know that may
demonstrate that you are interested in
in where this company is going if you're
interested if you're interviewing with
one of the more controversial companies
out there and there are many then you
might want to ask that question Point
plank not because you're you're casting
down on the company but you can you want
to see what is your position on this
you've been working and then the second
the second sort of secondary question I
would ask and you got to be careful with
this one because if you ask it if you
ask it early you might end up getting in
trouble so and I asked this on my
question I said can you describe your
role on the company to me so you turn it
around and you interview them you
interview the team that's interviewing
you and you get them to talk about
themselves and if there's one key to
building relationships of trust it's
getting somebody to talk about themsel
and listening to them so you have been
talking about how awesome you are this
whole time and in the back of their mind
a couple of them are probably going like
well damn you know that's cool oh that
person's just flexing God what who does
this person think they are but as soon
as you start building a relationship
with with the people who are
interviewing and there's some people who
know this technique and they will fight
back they'll like oh he's trying to be
my friend now no you don't have to ask
inauthentically you say something like
this you say you know what what you can
you would would you guys would you would
yall would yall mind describing your
role in the company and how long you've
been in the company and what you enjoy
most about working for the company many
of them will actually jump at the chance
to tell you when I did this once I
learned that one of the people that was
interviewing me had been in the position
for 20 years no way I was like oh my God
that was so cool I was able to show
legitimate you know sincere appreciation
for that kind of commitment to that
particular role in the company and and I
said well tell me about that how did
that work well I actually started out
doing medical technology I said oh
that's so cool I want I was going to I
was thinking about medical technology at
one point too and then they're like yeah
and then I got into this and then I
started doing this and I started out
doing this and this and this and they
give you their raise me now you have
built a relationship already with a
potential future team member so when it
comes time to evaluate you they're going
to remember that you showed sincere
interest in the company and the team
that means you asked questions about the
company that show that you've done the
research about the company and number
two you've done research about or you've
asked about the members of the team now
some of them are going to say no I don't
have to tell you any of that you're the
one in being interviewed and there are
people who will do that I've actually
been in an interview where I I attempted
to build a relationship with trust and
hear about someone and they go and they
literally said well you're the one being
interviewed and they they kind of
snarkily shut up and it was usually the
It's usually the the It's usually the
overworked engineer that they pulled in
to evaluate whether you're going to be
technically able to do the thing and
usually there will have been they will
have felt sincerely and very threatened
the whole time because your skills are
on par or better than theirs and and I
got to tell you you got to watch out for
that person who's on the team I've been
that person on the team when you're
doing a job interview there's going to
be a subject matter expert who's not
going to have particularly good social
skills who is an exp ERT they are really
good at technology and they they they
like being the king of the castle and if
and if they see you as a threat or if
they see you as somebody that they can't
work with I mean that's the hardest
person to win over because that's the
person who's actually going to say you
know something and and frankly it
depends on how the other team is managed
but if somebody on the team says if if
that person says well they seem I know
what they're doing but whatever you know
what I mean that's going to be High
Praise from that kind of person there's
going to be one or two other people that
have social skills and particularly the
hiring manager and they'll want to tell
you everything it doesn't hurt to
attempt to build relationships with
trust and and you can ask this question
very sincerely and if they say we don't
have time to talk about us I say well
you know in order for me to take this
position I'm just I'm just curious to
understand why you why you're working
for this team what are your motivations
for working for the team because I I
have my own motivations but I I'd like
to know about your history and your
motivations why what do you enjoy about
working here and I think that's a very
legitimate very sincere very humble
question and if they shut you down and
say we don't have time for that fine
you've at least attempted to demonstrate
interest in the team that you're about
to be working for you have demonstrated
interest in the company that you're
working for by doing that and you have
ended by asking questions that are in
sort of a present tense or a future
tense like so when I start with you guys
what is the one thing that you would
have me learn that's going to get me
going so we don't have to you know it's
going to it's going to reduce in my
amount of time so you you got them
thinking that you're already on the team
you're already interacting with
potential future members of the team
including the potential manager as if
you are on the team and the last
question you end with is when I'm
working with you guys so when I start
with you guys what is the one thing I
could learn right now today that I that
would make me immediately productive
that you need the most help with so I
can get going on it right now and then
you leave the interview and you shake
hands or if you're in person if not
you're like thank you very much this
sounds like a fantastic team legitimate
if you don't like the team don't say
that they'll see through it don't lie if
if the team if the interview go well and
the team is not like legitimately
interested in you and you're not jelling
with the team then say thank you very
much for your time and then leave but
don't lie don't pretend like you're
their best buddy they'll see right
through that but if you ask those
legitimate questions you may actually
open up an opportunity to build
relationships with trust and then you
might op that that relationship of trust
is going to directly lead to employment
because trust is the nature of
employment employment is about trust
I've done a whole video about that
before so focus on that and I think
you'll do fine make sure your Tech
skills are up to par make sure you're
honest that means if somebody if they
ask you about something you don't lie
say like in my interview I said Point
Blank I've never done kubernetes I've
played around with it in a home lab a
little bit but I don't have any
kubernetes skills and they said that's
fine and they got kind of like you know
you're you're fine you can learn it
right because there was other things
that my raise me and because I was
forthcoming and didn't say oh yeah I've
got 20 years of per you know I didn't
lie then they were okay with it now I I
I think that that is the that is a lot
of advice but again the entire interview
is for you to is an opportunity for you
to build relationships and trust with
your future team and to get them
assuming you're a member of the team
already by the time you leave just keep
that in your mind above everything else
all right hopefully that video was fine
um and and we'll go further on that oh
you got a starlink a starlink min's
confirmed okay well we're going to talk
about that stop recording